<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
 %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="general-genlib">
  <?dbhtml filename="genlib.html"?>

  <title>General Libraries</title>

  <para>
    Libraries contain code which is often required by more than
    one program.  This has the advantage that each program doesn't need to
    duplicate code (and risk introducing bugs), it just has to call
    functions from the libraries installed on the system.  The most obvious
    example of a set of libraries is <application>Glibc</application> which is
    installed during the LFS book.  This contains all of the
    <application>C</application> library functions which programs use.
  </para>

  <para>
    There are two types of libraries: static and shared.  Shared libraries
    (usually <filename>libXXX.so</filename>) are loaded into memory from the
    shared copy at runtime (hence the name).  Static libraries (<filename>
    libXXX.a</filename>) are actually linked into the program executable file
    itself, thus making the program file larger.  Quite often, you will find
    both static and shared copies of the same library on your system.
  </para>

  <para>
    Generally, you only need to install libraries when you are
    installing software that needs the functionality they supply.  In
    the BLFS book, each package is presented with a list of (known)
    dependencies.  Thus, you can figure out which libraries you need to have
    before installing that program.  If you are installing something without
    using BLFS instructions, usually the <filename>README</filename> or
    <filename>INSTALL</filename> file will contain
    details of the program's requirements.
  </para>

  <para>
    There are certain libraries which nearly <emphasis>everyone</emphasis> will
    need at some point.  In this chapter these and some others are listed and
    it is explained why you may want to install them.
  </para>

 

</sect1>
